Finding aid for Interlochen Center for The Arts Records, 1927-2005
Bentley Historical Library
- Chronological, 1920-1966
  - Subject Files, 1928-1989
    - Interlochen (Camp and Academy)
      - Michigan, State of
        "Michigan" (10), 1936-1988, focuses mainly on Camp relations with state government during the Maddy era, 1936-1965. Included are controversies over the development of Interlochen State Park, the relocation of the main highway, and a proposed prison camp (1953). It also covers gubernatorial appearances and attempts to secure legislative subsidies for performance trips (such as to the 1939 World's Fair) and promotional movies (which received aid from 1939 through 1954). Information on the controversy over the proposed Camp orchestra appearance at the Mackinac Bridge dedication (1958) can be found in "Petrillo controversy" (12) while the attempt in 1979 to locate a state prison camp near Interlochen is documented in Post-Maddy Administrators Jacobi.
        The State's cultural efforts are covered in files on the Michigan Cultural Commission (1960-1963) and the Michigan Council of the Arts (1963-1965). They show Maddy's work with Karl Haas, who later became President of Interlochen. On the Michigan Council of the Arts, researchers should also consult Post-Maddy Administrators Haas and Jacobi and Boal.
        Related materials concern the Michigan Youth Arts Festival, a Michigan Cultural Commission offspring (suggested in 1962 by William Stirton of the U. of M. and promoted by Maddy). Correspondence, minutes, and programs document its origins and subsequent development, especially the Interlochen auditions and Flint Michigan Week performances (sponsored by Harding Mott).
        - Legislative (mainly funding) and miscellanea
          - Correspondence, 1938-1940 (Box 34)
          - Season passes, 1940 (Box 34)
          - Correspondence, 1941-1942 (Box 34)
          - Season passes, 1942 (Box 34)
          - Correspondence, 1943 (Box 34)
          - Season passes, 1943 (Box 34)
          - Correspondence, 1944-1947; 2 folders (Box 34)
          - Correspondence, 1948-1965; 3 folders (Box 35)
        - Governors
          - Fitzgerald, Frank, 1936 (Box 35)
          - Murphy, Frank, 1938 (Box 35)
          - Van Wagoner, Murray, 1941-1942 (Box 35)
          - Dickinson, Loren, 1942 (Box 35)
          - Kelly, Harry, 1943-1946 (Box 35)
          - Sigler, Kim, 1947 (Box 35)
          - Williams, G. Mennen, 1949 (Box 35)
          - Swainson, John, 1961 (Box 35)
          - Romney, George
            - General, 1963-1965 (Box 35)
        - State of Michigan Scholarships, 1965 (Box 35)
        - Departments
          - Conservation
            - General, 1941-1948 (Box 35)
            - Interlochen State Park, 1944-1953; 1960-1963; 3 folders (Box 35)
            - North Manitou Island (W.K. Angell), 1944-1949 (Box 35)
          - Corrections
            - Prison Camp controversy, 1953
              - Correspondence (Box 35)
              - Clippings (Box 35)
            - Commission on Law Enforcement and Criminal Justice (meeting), 1971 (Box 35)
          - Highway, 1935-1965 (Box 35)
          - Liquor Control Commission, 1942-1955 (Box 35)
          - Public Instruction, 1943-1964 (Box 35)
        - Michigan Cultural Commission, 1960-1963; 2 folders (Box 35)
        - Michigan Council for the Arts, 1963-1965 (Box 35)
        - Michigan Youth Arts Festival
          - Papers (Michigan Week), 1955 (Box 35)
          - Papers, 1962-1966; 4 folders (Box 35)
          - Printed, 1963-1966 (Box 35)
          - Papers, 1971 (Box 35)
          - Papers, 1982-1988 (Box 35)
      - Organizations
        "Organizations" (11), 1935-1976, concern professional and support groups associated with Interlochen. Many of them provided gifts of buildings, scholarships, and music as well as held meetings there. Arranged alphabetically, the files include mainly correspondence but also some minutes, reports, and articles. Most relate to the Maddy era although items from the Haas and Jacobi presidencies are included. The Michigan Federation of Music Clubs files document the history of the group and its long association with Interlochen. Information on the American Bandmaster Association convention (1936) can be found in Chronological Camp files, 1935-1945.
        - American Bandmasters' Association, 1939-1962 (Box 35)
          (See also Box 3)
        - American Camping Association, Great Lakes Council, 1935-1945; 2 folders (Box 35)
        - American Society of Composers, Authors and Publishers, 1938-1946 (Box 35)
        - American String Teachers Association, 1950-1965 (Box 35)
        - Delta Omicron, 1954-1962 (Box 35)
        - Federation of Music Clubs
          - Michigan
            - 1935-1966, 62 folders (Box 35)
            - 1966-1974, 2 folders (Box 36)
          - Other states, 1936-1955 (Box 36)
          - National
            - 1936-1938 (Box 36)
            - Elementary school orchestra, 1938 (Box 36)
            - 1940-1969, 5 folders (Box 36)
        - Federation of Women's Clubs
          - Michigan, 1944-1976 (Box 36)
          - National, 1946; 1956-1957; 1966 (Box 36)
        - Michigan Council on Adult Education, 1943-1948 (Box 36)
        - Mu Phi Epsilon, 1947-1965 (Box 36)
        - National Music Council, 1938-1966; 1976 (Box 36)
        - Phi Mu Alpha (Sinfonia)
          - General, 1951-1961 (Box 36)
          - National Delegate Assembly, 1968-1970 (Box 36)
          - National Delegate Assembly, 1971-1973 (Box 36)
      - Petrillo controversy
        The "Petrillo Controversy" (12), 1930-1987, covers the American Federation of Musicians ban on broadcasting from (as well as teaching or performing at) Interlochen. It begins with overview accounts of the controversy and surviving documents on Maddy's earlier dealings with the musicians union. For the origins of the controversy, researchers will also want to check Subject Maddy "Music Education" under "Music Educators National Conference."
        Correspondence, testimony, notes, and newspaper articles document Maddy's efforts to lift the ban. The correspondence includes exchanges with many Congressmen, especially members of the Michigan delegation (particularly Senator Arthur Vandenberg and Congressman Albert Engel). Maddy also dealt extensively with Congressmen Clarence Lea of California and Carroll Kearns of Pennsylvania. Former Governor Wilber Brucker of Michigan, served as Maddy's legal counsel on the issue during the early 1950's.
        Because of bulk, the correspondence is sometimes separated into special (Maddy) and general files. The former includes individuals of particular importance on the issue, to the Camp or in society, while the latter contains general support letters (which often include responses from Congressmen). Researchers interested in the efforts to lift the ban should also consult the Giddings and Tremaine correspondence in Chronological Camp files, 1935-1966.
        The final portion on the Petrillo controversy deals with its settlement and the Camp's subsequent relations with the American Federation of Musicians and other unions, especially the United Automobile Workers. On the resolution of the controversy, researchers will also want to consult Post-Maddy Administrators Gillis.
        - History (Box 36)
        - Background-American Fed. of Musicians
          - Permission for broadcasts, 1930 (Box 36)
          - General, 1937-1940 (Box 36)
          - Ohio union issues, 1937-1939 (Box 36)
          - Clippings, 1940 (Box 36)
          - Paul Whiteman appearance, 1941 (Box 36)
          - Maddy letter to U.S. Attorney General, March 1942 (Box 36)
        - Union ban
          - Maddy papers, July-August, 1942; 2 folders (Box 36)
          - Maddy support letters, A-Z, July-August, 1942; 2 folders (Box 36)
          - Clippings, July-August 1942; 3 folders (Box 36)
          - Arthur Vandenberg correspondence, July-December 1942 (Box 36)
          - Maddy papers, September-December 1942 (Box 36)
          - Student committee records, September-Dec, 1942 (Box 36)
          - Clippings, September-December 1942 (Box 36)
          - Maddy papers, 1943 (Box 36)
          - Arthur Vandenberg correspondence, 1943 (Box 36)
          - General letters of support, January 1943 (Box 36)
          - Clippings, 1943 (Box 36)
          - Arthur Vandenberg correspondence, 1944 (Box 36)
          - Albert Engel correspondence, January-March 14, 1944 (Box 36)
          - Maddy papers, February-March 20, 1944 (Box 36)
          - Maddy testimony, Senate Interstate Commerce Committee, March 20, 1944 (Box 37)
          - Maddy papers, March 20-December 31, 1944; 2 folders (Box 37)
          - General letters of support, November-December 1944 (Box 37)
          - Clippings, 1944 (Box 37)
          - Arthur Vandenberg correspondence, 1945 (Box 37)
          - Maddy papers, January-February 21 1945; 2 folders (Box 37)
          - Maddy testimony, House Interstate Commerce Committee, February 22, 1945 (Box 37)
          - Maddy papers, February 23-December 31, 1945; 4 folders (Box 37)
          - General letters of support, 1945; 2 folders (Box 37)
          - Maddy notes, circa, 1945 (Box 37)
          - Clippings, 1945 (Box 37)
          - National Association of Broadcasters, AFM bulletins and related printed, 1942-1945 (Box 37)
          - Requests for booklet, "Young America Fights for Constitutional Rights,", November 1945-January 1946 (Box 37)
          - Committee for Constitutional Government, corresp., 1946-1948 (Box 37)
          - Maddy papers, January-February 15, 1946 (Box 37)
          - General letters of support, January-February 15, 1946 (Box 37)
          - Maddy papers, February 16-March 31, 1946 (Box 37)
          - General letters of support, February 16-March 31, 1946 (Box 37)
          - Maddy papers, April-December 1946 (Box 37)
          - General letters of support, April-December 1946 (Box 37)
          - Clippings, 1946 (Box 37)
          - Maddy papers, January-February 17, 1947 (Box 37)
          - Maddy testimony, House Committee on Education and Labor, February 18, 1947 (Box 37)
          - Maddy papers, February 18-December 31, 1947; 2 folders (Box 37)
          - Clippings, 1947 (Box 37)
          - Printed hearings and report of House Committee on Education and Labor, June 27-August 7, 1947 (Box 38)
          - Coronet magazine article, papers re, October 1947-March 1948 (Box 38)
          - Maddy history of controversy, 1947-1948 (Box 38)
          - Maddy testimony, House Committee on Education and Labor, January 16, 1948 (Box 38)
          - Maddy papers, 1948 (Box 38)
          - Clippings, 1948 (Box 38)
          - Maddy papers, 1949 (Box 38)
          - Maddy papers, October 1952-April 13, 1953 (Box 38)
          - Maddy testimony, Senate Committee on Labor and Public Welfare, April 14, 1953 (Box 38)
          - Printed hearings
            - Senate Labor and Public Welfare Committee, April 14-21, 1953 (Box 38)
            - House Education and Labor Committee, April 17-22, 1953 (Box 38)
          - Maddy papers, April 18-December 31, 1953 (Box 38)
          - Maddy papers, 1954-1957 (Box 38)
          - Maddy papers, January-June 3, 1958 (Box 38)
          - Scrapbook on Mackinac Bridge Controversy, May 7, 1958 (Box 38)
          - Maddy testimony, House Education and Labor Committee, June 3, 1958 (Box 38)
          - Maddy papers, June 4-December 31, 1958 (Box 38)
          - Clippings, 1953-1958; undated (Box 38)
          - Miscellaneous printed, 1946-1952; undated (Box 38)
        - Reconciliation
          - Maddy/Gillis papers, 1959-1961 (Box 38)
          - Maddy papers, 1962-1964 (Box 38)
          - Permission for Chicago concert, 1968 (Box 38)
          - Clippings, 1962-1984 (Box 38)
          - Lea Act, 1978-1984 (Box 38)
          - Music Performance Trust Fund, 1987 (Box 38)
        - United Automobile Workers, music scholarship, 1962-1964 (Box 38)
      - Publicity/Promotion, 1939-1972
        "Publicity/Promotion" (13), 1939-1972, covers both staff and commercial endeavors. The former concern Interlochen's own print, film, and recording efforts. Correspondence, manuscript writings, press releases, and publications, 1946-1971, are included. For earlier publicity efforts, researchers should check Chronological Camp files, 1935-1945 under "Publicity." They will also find the Publications and Scrapbooks series useful.
        The commercial section deals with outside film and television productions about Interlochen. It includes documentation on the Paramount movie There's Magic in Music (1940), and the "Today" Show telecast (1963). The former includes correspondence, plot outlines, publicity releases, and scripts, and alludes to the war's effect on studio film making.
        - Internal productions
          - Print
            - Norma Lee Browning (Ogg) correspondence, 1946 (Box 38)
            - Maddy correspondence, 1947-1948 (Box 38)
            - Maddy correspondence, 1961; 1963-1965 (Box 38)
            - Correspondence, 1966-1971 (Box 38)
            - Stories (Hollingsworth, Bickering, Norton, and others), circa, 1931-1940 (Box 38)
            - Comments about Camp, circa, 1930s-1970s (Box 38)
            - Leonard de Vries account, 1952-1956 (Box 38)
              (see Box 2: Chrono.-Camp History)
            - Camper article for Instrumentalist, 1964 (Box 38)
            - Press releases and articles, 1941-1968 (Box 38)
            - Publicity for Academy, 1960-1968 (Box 38)
            - Printed promotional materials, 1940-1960 (Box 38)
          - Movies
            - Camp, papers, 1944-1950 (Box 38)
            - Camp, papers, 1951-1956 (Box 38)
            - Scripts, 1947; 1950; undated (Box 38)
            - String Class Teaching at Interlochen, Ogg/Browning scene outline, circa, 1960 (Box 38)
            - Academy, papers, 1962-1963 (Box 38)
            - Script, "The Three R's and the Arts" (Academy), 1963 (Box 38)
            - Maddy Memorial fund-raiser, 1966 (Box 38)
            - "Michigan and the Arts,", 1968 (Box 38)
          - RCA Recording Division (Lucy Johnson-Van Cliburn performance), 1964-1965 (Box 38)
        - Commercial productions (Box 38)
        - Movies
          - Paramount, "There's Magic in Music"
            - History (Box 38)
            - Papers, 1939 (Box 38)
            - Papers, 1940-1944; 6 folders (Box 38)
            - Script, undated (Box 38)
            - Alumni letters, August-September 1941 (Box 38)
            - Clippings, 1940-1941 (Box 38)
          - Ann Ronell/Lester Cowan
            - Correspondence, 1941-1956 (Box 38)
            - Papers re proposed TV film, 1960-1961 (Box 38)
            - 1963-1964, 1972 correspondence, 1963-1972 (Box 38)
          - Jesse Lasky (MGM), correspondence, 1953-1955 (Box 38)
          - Walt Disney Productions (also TV), Gillis/Maddy correspondence, 1959-1962 (Box 38)
          - Finnegan Pinchuk Co., "Moving Target," permission request, 1986-1987 (Box 38)
        - TV
          (see also movies)
          - WWTV (Cadillac) 1954 (Camp) and 1962 (Maddy), 1954-1962 (Box 38)
          - CBS News, 1962 (Box 38)
          - Today Show (Hugh Downs), 1962-1964 (Box 38)
          - French television, 1964-1965 (Box 38)
          - Canadian television, 1965 (Box 38)
          - WOOD (Grand Rapids) (Maddy), 1967 (Box 38)
          - Westinghouse TV (WJZ), 1968 (Box 38)
        - Videotape (Communications Center Promotion), 1972 (Box 38)
      - Special Events, 1948-1989
        "Special Events" (14), 1948-1989, documents activities which the Office of Special Events now handles: post-camp conferences, off-campus performances, and domestic visitors. Post-camp conference materials, 1951-1989, include correspondence on planning and arrangements as well as informational literature.
        Similar materials characterize the off-campus performances by Interlochen groups. They are divided into appearances by the Camp, 1948-1972, and Academy, 1963-88. The former covers trips to the Mackinac Bridge dedication, 1958 (see Petrillo controversy), and the White House, 1962. The Academy portion includes in-state outreach tours sponsored by the Michigan Council for the Arts as well as appearances at Lincoln Center (1964), Carnegie Hall (1969), and Kennedy Center (1972) and a Choir trip to Denmark (1973). Information on earlier tours can be found in the Chronological Camp files, 1935-1945 while foreign visitors are covered under "International" (8) and "International Society of Music Educators" (9) in this sub-subseries.
        - Post-Camp conferences
          - Accordions, 1958-1963; 1974 (Box 39)
          - Adult
            - Papers, 1951-1973 (Box 39)
            - Printed, 1951-1989 (Box 39)
          - American Recorder Society, 1967; 1971 (Box 39)
          - Bands, 1958-1974 (Box 39)
          - Chamber Music Conference, 1969-1970 (Box 39)
          - Chamber Music America, 1978; 1984-1985 (Box 39)
          - Lutheran Ashram, 1948-1949 (Box 39)
          - Michigan Square Dance Leaders Association, 1962-1966 (Box 39)
          - Red Cross Aquatic School, 1968-1970 (Box 39)
          - String-Class Teaching Workshop, 1966-1971 (Box 39)
          - Writers Conference, 1968 (Box 39)
        - Trips/special appearances
          - Camp
            - Grand Rapids, 1948 (Box 39)
            - Mackinac Bridge, 1958 (Box 39)
              (see Petrillo controversy)
            - Dearborn, 1962 (Box 39)
            - White House, 1962; 2 folders (Box 39)
            - Dearborn, 1963 (Box 39)
            - Detroit (NEA convention), 1963 (Box 39)
            - Luci Johnson appearance, 1964 (Box 39)
            - Watergate (Washington, D.C.), 1964 (Box 39)
            - Ann Arbor, 1969 (Box 39)
          - Joint (Camp and Academy)
            - Miscellaneous, 1963-1972 (Box 39)
            - New York World's Fair (proposed), 1964-1965 (Box 39)
            - Highlight summary, 1967-1972 (Box 39)
          - Academy
            - Philadelphia (MENC convention) and New York (Lincoln Center), 1963-1964 (Box 39)
            - Chicago and Richmond, Ind., 1965 (Box 40)
              (See also Box 1)
            - Michigan and Illinois, 1966 (Box 40)
            - Eastern and Canada, 1966 (Box 40)
            - Eastern and Canada, 1967 (Box 40)
            - Miscellaneous, 1963-1968 (Box 40)
            - Chicago, 1968-1969 (Box 40)
            - Carnegie Hall, 1969-1970 (Box 40)
            - Miscellaneous, 1969-1970 (Box 40)
            - White House Conference on Children and Youth, 1970 (Box 40)
            - Columbia, Md., and Washington (Kennedy Center), 1972; 2 folders (Box 40)
            - Miscellaneous, 1971-1972 (Box 40)
            - Denmark (Choir), 1973 (Box 40)
            - Miscellaneous, 1973-1976 (Box 40)
            - Detroit, 1976 (Box 40)
            - Ann Arbor (Messiah), 1967-1977 (Box 40)
            - Detroit Symphony Orchestra, Schubert Festival, 1978 (Box 40)
            - Miscellaneous, 1978-1988 (Box 40)
            - Interlochen Outreach (Michigan Council of the Arts), printed programs, 1979-1988 (Box 40)
        - Visitors (Domestic)
          (see also Box 47; for International see Boxes 33 and 34)
          - General, 1948; 1961-1972 (Box 40)
          - Concerts, 1966-1974 (Box 40)
          - Conventions and meetings, 1961-1977 (Box 40)
        - Special Events Office, job analyses and reports, 1965-1966 (Box 40)
      - Traverse City
        "Traverse City" (15), 1958-1969, offers fragmentary materials on Interlochen's relations with its home area. Included is a geography master's thesis (1965) on the Camp's economic impact. More detailed information about the relations with the Grand Traverse region can be found in "Fund Raising" (5), "Michigan" (10), and "U. S. Government" (16) in this sub-subseries as well as the Giddings and Tremaine correspondence in the Chronological Camp files, 1935-1966 and the Boards Control series.
        - Rotary, 1960-1963 (Box 40)
        - General, 1958-1969 (Box 40)
        - Masters thesis re Camp's economic impact on the area, circa, 1965 (Box 40)
      - United States Government, 1934-1977
        Dealings with federal officials and units are detailed in "United States Government"(16), 1934-1977. Matters covered include the Federal Music Project (1937-1948), operational problems during World War II, postwar construction projects, the Jet Air Base controversy (1954-1957), and the HEW grant for an Honors Musicianship Project (1964-1968). Michigan congressional leaders are well represented in the correspondence. On federal government matters, researchers will also want to consult "International" (8) and "Petrillo controversy" (12) as well as the Giddings and Tremaine correspondence in the Chronological Camp files, 1935-1966.
        - General correspondence, 1934-1977; 6 folders (Box 40)
        - Federal Music Project (WPA), 1937-1948 (Box 40)
        - Jet Air Base controversy
          - History, 1954-1955 (Box 40)
          - Papers, March-December 1954; 2 folders (Box 40)
          - Report, Traverse City presentation, 1954 (Box 41)
          - Report, documentation of Traverse City versus Cadillac sites, 1955 (Box 41)
          - Papers, 1955-1956 (Box 41)
          - Scrapbook, clippings, 1955-1957 (Box 41)
          - Clippings (loose), 1955-1956 (Box 41)
        - Curriculum study grant (HEW), 1964-1968; 2 folders (Box 41)
          (see also Box 24)
      - University of Michigan
        "University of Michigan" (17), mainly 1940-1970, concerns Interlochen's relations with its major academic partner. Most pertains to the Camp, especially the University/All State Division, from 1942 on. It also covers the university financial loan to the Camp (1953) when a major building (the hotel) needed replacement. Correspondence with university officials as well as draft and final agreements and reports of the Director of the University Division are included. Researchers will again find the Giddings and Tremaine correspondence in the Chronological Camp files (I-C and D) most helpful.
        - History of Camp relationship (by Maddy), 1960 (Box 41)
        - Correspondence and agreements, 1930; 1940-1970; 5 folders (Box 41)
        - Summer Science Training Program, 1962-1963 (Box 41)
        - Director's reports, University Division, 1950-1963; 3 folders (Box 41)
    - Camp, 1928-1989
      Camp sub-subseries, 1928-1989, offers detailed operational materials on the summer program. Coverage is best from the late 1930's through late 1960's and includes much mimeographed material. Rosters, forms, memos, statistics, reports, and similar type items predominate while correspondence is sparse. Unit and divisional reports, constituting approximately half the total sub-subseries, give elaborate accounts of non-musical activities at the Camp, but are confined almost exclusively to the 1960's and are heavily oriented to girls' division. The planning and recommendation files give the reflective comments of staff members on their experiences with programs and suggestions for the future.
      The materials present a variety of potential research uses. While application forms reflect changing admission standards, enrollment statistics (compiled by Maddy) and rosters indicate how many were in Camp, who they were, and what they did. Course materials include items on Maddy's string instrument workshop, to which he devoted increasing emphasis as bands grew in popularity on the high school level. Informational materials indicate the parameters in which students, staff, and faculty were expected to operate. Student government items are also included. The sub-subseries serves as an especially useful supplement to the Chronological Camp files, 1935-1966
      - Application forms
        - High school, 1928-1989; 2 folders (Box 41)
        - Junior, 1944-1989 (Box 41)